Finding Aid for Arthur Gallagher Papers, 1947-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Gallagher Papers 1947-1992, 1947-1976
Gallagher, Arthur.
8 linear feet
85167 Aa 2
Editor of the Ann Arbor News, 1954-1976. Personal and professional correspondence, photographs, editorials, editorial topical files, and speeches; also organizational files relating to the Booth Newspaper chain and the Ann Arbor News, and to other professional, civic, and charitable organizations, notably the Michigan Press Association, the University Press Club of Michigan, and the Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was the gift of Arthur Gallagher (donor no. 6281 ) and came to the library in 1979.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur Gallagher was born in Manistique, Michigan on May 16, 1911. While a high school student Gallagher covered school sporting events for the local paper, the South Haven Daily Tribune, during the school term and did general reporting during the summer. He became a full time employee following graduation, remaining with the paper for two years working as a reporter, sports editor, and circulation manager. In 1931 Gallagher moved to Ann Arbor where he enrolled at The University of Michigan and began working for The Ann Arbor Tribune. He attended the University until 1935 when he dropped out to go to work at the Tribune on a full time basis. He completed his studies through the University's extension program. Finally in 1976, he received his Bachelor of Arts degree.
At the Tribune, Gallagher worked as a reporter, circulation manager, and editor-manager. In 1937 Gallagher moved to the Ann Arbor News, which was a subsidiary of Booth Newspapers, Inc., where he worked at various times as the county, telegraph, and news editor.
Gallagher replaced Ralph N. Byers as editor of the News after Byers untimely death on August 10, 1954. Gallagher remained editor until his retirement on June 1, 1976.
Much of the material contained in the Gallagher papers pertains either to the news and editorial operations of the Ann Arbor News or to the management and business of running the newspaper. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Ann Arbor News general correspondence and memoranda; Editorials and Editorial Subject files; Articles and Speeches; Organizational files; Miscellaneous Topical Files; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce.; Ann Arbor news.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Booth Newspapers, Inc.; Journalists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Press Association.; American newspapers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University Press Club of Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor news.; Demonstrations.; Historic buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Lions International.; Newspaper industry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Graduation ceremonies--1964.; Victory celebrations--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Ann Arbor News general correspondence and memoranda
  The Ann Arbor News general correspondence and memoranda series contains reader correspondence commenting on local happenings and on the content and format of the News. This series also includes inter-office memoranda and miscellaneous correspondence.
  - 1954-June 1965, 38 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1965-June 1975, 34 folders (Box 2)
  - July 1975-May 1976, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Editorials and Editorial Subject files
  The Editorials and Editorial Subject files includes some of the newsman's editorials as well as additional relevant material such as correspondence, source material, and memoranda filed by subject.
  - Editorials written by Arthur Gallagher 1954-1976 (Box 3)
  - Subject files
    - Child Adoption Project 1967-1976 (Box 3)
    - Civil Rights
      - Undated (Box 3)
      - 1956-1963 (Box 3)
      - 1964 (Box 3)
      - 1965 (Box 3)
      - 1969-1974 (Box 3)
    - Demonstrations (public and student unrest) 1966-1974 (Box 3)
    - Performance of Ann Arbor News in reporting political news
      - 1956-1966 (Box 3)
      - 1966-1976 (Box 3)
      - Undated and miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Pornography 1967-1974 (Box 3)
    - Seat Belts 1955-1972 (Box 3)
    - Taking Judges out of Politics 1957, 1960, 1964 (Box 3)
    - The United Fund 1954-1956 and 1963, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Vietnam 1966-1974, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw Community College 1962-1965 (Box 3)
- Articles and Speeches
  The Articles and Speeches series contains a few articles as well as copies of a number of speeches delivered by Gallagher between 1959 and 1979, many of which deal with topics related to journalism. Included with Gallagher's works are transcripts of two of three interviews conducted by a University of Michigan student with Gallagher in 1978 as part of an oral history assignment. The paper which resulted from this assignment is also present. The interviews and paper focus on Gallagher's role as editor of the News, but also include valuable biographical information.
  - Articles
    - "School Role of the Layman," printed in A Report On The Little White House Conference, December 8, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Youths' Military Obligations 1954 (Box 3)
      (includes notes, correspondence and source material from series of articles)
  - Speeches
    - Schools and Public Relations circa 1959 (Box 3)
    - Managed News May 1963 (Box 3)
    - "A Catholic Editor and the Press," Winter 1964 (Box 3)
    - "Newspapers Need Youth," November 14, 1964 (Box 3)
    - The Press Today November 30, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Challenges in Reporting Sensitive Stories May 9, 1966 (Box 3)
    - "Does Medicine Have A 'Bad Press'?" April 4, 1967 (Box 3)
    - The Need for a Local Historical Museum May 15, 1967 (Box 3)
    - "The Role of the Press in Creating Public Awareness about Critical Community Problems," circa 1968 (Box 3)
    - "Building A 'Political Image'?" Summer 1968 (Box 3)
    - Review of Gallagher's Career at Ann Arbor News 1975 (Box 3)
    - "Civil Rights in Ann Arbor, " April 2, 1979 (Box 3)
    - "Islands, religions and kings," December 1980 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous speeches (Box 4)
      (include Dunworkin Club speech, May 1982)
    - Speech note cards (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Paper, title unknown, on Arthur Gallagher, written in 1978 by University of Michigan student Judy Rakowsky, 23 pages (Box 4)
    - Rakowsky/Gallagher interview #1, transcript February 10, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Rakowsky/Gallagher interview #3, transcript March 22, 1978 (Box 4)
- Organizational files
  The Organizational files series has been arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization. In addition to Booth Newspapers and the Ann Arbor News many professional and civic organizations are represented. These reflect Gallagher's interest in education, the establishment of professional standards in journalism, and civic affairs. Included among the organizations with which Gallagher was involved are the Inland Daily Press Association, the Michigan Associated Press Editorial Association, the American Red Cross, the Michigan Press Association, and the University Press Club of Michigan.
  - Booth Newspapers, Inc.
    - Correspondence 1953-1976, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Assessment Center 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - International Typographical Union Negotiations 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Recruiting, Indiana University 1969-1972 (Box 4)
    - Training program 1965-1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Washington, D.C. Bureau 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - The Ann Arbor News
    - Amelia Earhart Commemorative Flight 1967 (Box 4)
    - Byers, Ralph N., miscellaneous correspondence 1947-1950, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Case files:
      - Falsification of credentials by Mildred Bautista, Assistant to the Ann Arbor Superintendent of Schools 1972 (Box 4)
      - 1974 stabbing of Tom Campbell (Box 4)
      - Arrest for shoplifting of Jack Elzay, Ann Arbor Superintendent of Schools 1966 (Box 4)
    - Circulation
      - 1953-1960 (Box 4)
      - 1961-1976 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Conversion to Cold Type 1964-1976, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Editorial Association 1968-1974 (Box 4)
    - Editorial Department Annual Reports 1950-1969 (Box 4)
    - Editorial Expenses 1953-1971 (Box 4)
    - Editorial Staff 1947-1973 (Box 4)
    - Features 1954-1956 (Box 4)
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation 1956-1971 (Box 4)
    - Feminism 1972-1975 (Box 4)
    - Foreign Language Features, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Free Press-Fair Trial
      - 1964 undated (Box 4)
      - 1965 (Box 5)
      - 1966-1970 (Box 5)
    - Friend of the Court October 1967 (Box 5)
    - Goals Review 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Good Morning Michigan, 1973-1975 (Box 5)
    - Huron Valley Advisor 1964, 1972 (Box 5)
    - International Typographical Union Strike 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - League of Women Voters 1955-1974 (Box 5)
    - Letters to the Editor (Box 5)
      (evaluative study and related material)
    - Lingo-Matic (learning Russian by newspaper) 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - Moral Re-Armament Assembly 1958-1962 (Box 5)
    - Paid Obituary Policy 1965-1975 (Box 5)
    - Readers Viewpoint, letters received
      - March 1-15, 1962 (Box 5)
      - March 16-31, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Science Beat 1962-1964 (Box 5)
    - Selection of Managing Editor 1974 (Box 5)
    - Style Book 1953, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Sunday Edition 1953-1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Television Magazine 1974 (Box 5)
    - Unidentified Flying Objects 1965-1968 (Box 5)
    - Urban-Renewal 1959 (Box 5)
    - Video Display Terminal System 1973-1975, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Visual Education Center 1961-1963 (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw County Board of Supervisors (opening of meetings) 1966 (Box 5)
    - Whitmore Lake Town Meeting (letter writing campaign) October 1964 (Box 5)
    - Willow Run Airport 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - Ypsilanti News Coverage
      - Undated 1960-1964 (Box 5)
      - 1965-1968 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - American Red Cross, Washtenaw County Chapter
    - Correspondence and memoranda undated, 1956-1970, 7 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and memoranda 1971-1976, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Building campaign 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Associated Press Managing Editors Association
    - Women In the Newsroom 1967 (Box 6)
    - State Studies Committee and Miscellaneous 1967-1971 (Box 6)
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors
    - Editor in Residence Program 1969-1973 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1969-1973 (Box 6)
  - Inland Daily Press Association
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1961-1963, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Journalism Education, Personnel Recruiting and Training undated, 1962-1964, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Michigan Associated Press Editorial Association
    - Correspondence 1957-1975, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Annual meeting 1958 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous meeting materials undated, 1955-1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Newsphoto and Newswriting Contests undated, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    - Nominating Committee 1964-1966 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Press Association
    - Correspondence and Memoranda undated, 1959-1968, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Career Carnival 1964 (Box 6)
    - Elections to Board 1966-1967, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Journalism Education Committee
      - 1959-1961 (Box 6)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 7)
      - 1964-1971 (Box 7)
    - Nominating Committee 1967 (Box 7)
    - Traffic Safety Committee 1955-1975 (Box 7)
  - Michigan State News
    - Correspondence and Memoranda undated, 1970-1972, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Applications 1972 (Box 7)
  - The United Fund, Washtenaw County Chapter
    - 1955-1972 (Box 7)
    - Campaign Chairman Selection Committee 1969-1977 (Box 7)
    - Public Relations Committee 1971 (Box 7)
  - University Press Club of Michigan
    - 1957-1959 (Box 7)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 7)
    - 1966-1973 (Box 7)
    - Communism and Main Street, USA, addresses and discussions, 42nd annual meeting, Ann Arbor, October 16-17, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Foreign Journalism Fellowships 1960 (Box 7)
    - Journalism Fellowship Program (Interns) 1957-1959 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Topical Files
  - Advisory Committee for a Press Institute on China, The University of Michigan 1967-1969 (Box 7)
  - American Cancer Society 1957-1959 (Box 7)
  - American Council on Education for Journalism (accreditation) 1962-1972 (Box 7)
  - American Press Institute Editors Seminar May 21-June 1, 1962, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce
    - 1957-1966 (Box 7)
    - Central Business District Committee 1961-1962 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Affairs Committee 1970-1973, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Education Committee
      - 1958-1960 (Box 7)
      - Community College 1959-1967 (Box 7)
      - Source materials, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Traffic Committee, 1958-1962 (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor Freedom Festival 1955 (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor Mayor's Committee on Efficiency 1966, 1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Citizens' Advisory Committee for Finance, Subcommittee for Financial Analysis 1967 (Box 8)
  - Citizens Blue Ribbon Committee on Problems of Drug Abuse
    - Reports 1969-1970 (Box 8)
    - Committee meeting summaries April-September 1970 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence and Memoranda 1970-1975 (Box 8)
    - Newspaper coverage 1970-1974 (Box 8)
    - Source materials (local) (Box 8)
    - Source materials (general) (Box 8)
  - Krueger, Lawrence F. and the Pittsfield School District 1948-1958 (Box 8)
  - Lions Club Eye Bank
    - Undated 1956-1959 (Box 8)
    - 1960-1970 (Box 8)
    - Eye Bank News circa 1961-1971 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Citizens Council for Better Schools 1958-1959 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Constitutional Convention 1960-1963 (Box 8)
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, Inc., Washtenaw County Chapter 1958, 1962 (Box 8)
  - National Library Week 1966 (Box 8)
  - Michigan State Steering Committee 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - National Security Forum 1962-1963 (Box 8)
  - Pulitzer Prize Journalism Jury 1974-1976 (Box 8)
  - Regional Press Council Study 1974-1975 (Box 8)
  - Southeastern Michigan Science Fair 1958-1977, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Temporary Steering Committee for a Repertory Theater, Ann Arbor 1959-1960 (Box 8)
  - United Fund and Community Services, Inc. 1962-1964, 1976-1977 (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Photographs, 4 envelopes (Box 8)
    Photographs, many of them probably from the Ann Arbor News, include views of Ann Arbor, Michigan, historic homes and public occasions; also photographs detailing Gallagher's other interests, notably the Lion's Club Eye Bank program.
  - Lectures given in retirement to the Dunworkin Club 1980-1992 (Box 8)